<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Coding Diet (casperjs)</title><link>https://allanderek.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://allanderek.github.io/categories/casperjs.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 May 2016 18:44:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Selenium vs CasperJS</title><link>https://allanderek.github.io/posts/selenium-and-casper/</link><dc:creator>Allan Clark</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have a web service using a Python web framework such as Flask.
So you wish to do a full user test by automating the browser. Should you use
the Python bindings to Selenium or CasperJS? In this post I wish to detail some
of the advantages and drawbacks of both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Python + Selenium Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is fairly straightforward. You are simply writing some Python code that
happens to call a library which binds to Selenium. In order for this to work
you will need to install phantomJS but using &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; this is pretty trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Javascript + CasperJS Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say Javascript, but at least when I'm using casperJS it tends to be from
Coffeescript, but whichever is your fancy works well enough. Similarly to the
above you will need to install casperJS through the &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; but again this is
pretty trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my sample project the casperJS tests are faster, by quite a bit. This
certainly warrants some more investigation as to exactly why this is the case,
but for now my sample project runs the casperJS tests in around 3 seconds whilst
the Selenium ones take around 12 seconds to do the same amount of work. I'm not
sure whether this is a constant factor or whether it will get worse with more
tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://allanderek.github.io/posts/selenium-and-casper/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>casperjs</category><category>python</category><category>selenium</category><category>testing</category><guid>https://allanderek.github.io/posts/selenium-and-casper/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2016 11:11:40 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>